<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: politics | BLog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bleonard.github.io/blog/categories/politics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bleonard.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-14T15:13:13-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://bleonard.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brian Leonard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Post Election]]></title>
    <link href="http://bleonard.github.io/blog/2016/11/10/post-election/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://bleonard.github.io/blog/2016/11/10/post-election</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been thinking a lot about the book <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_City_%26_the_City"><em>The City &amp; the City</em></a> by China Miéville. It describes a town in which two sets of people share the same physical space but do not acknowledge each other. For that matter, they are forbidden to do so.</p>

<p>I remember being surprised in 1992 when Bill Clinton won the election. I lived in Texas and everyone I knew was voting for Bush. Now, I live in California and the same thing snuck up on me again this week. There's very little learning there.</p>

<p>But it's not just where I live because technology has allowed a nation like in the book. Today, my Twitter feed is filled with anxiety, sadness, outrage, and very scared people. I am certain there are people nearby, not to mention in all those (many) red states, that have an exceptionally different feed: one full of hope, expectation, and triumph. And there is no connection between the two.</p>

<p>In that 1992 election, it was the economy (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/It%27s_the_economy,_stupid">stupid</a>) and the need for change. I'm certainly not a political analyst, but that rings just as true this week. All the jobs numbers are up over the last 8 years, but not everywhere and not for everyone. This has caused a rift.</p>

<h2>Forward</h2>

<p>Where do we go from here? I believe it's best for each of use to use our talents and position as leverage to make a difference. In my case, I can help literally provide work in these areas of the country.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.taskrabbit.com">TaskRabbit</a> has been focusing on its largest markets because there is still plenty of room to grow there. And the whole thing is a hard problem. The focus helps, but our map is somewhat bare in Middle America. For me, this election is a kick in the pants to get there sooner than later.</p>

<p>The biggest fail there would be to believe that we can "save" people from on high by bestowing the magic of technology. Fortunately, even as the chief technologist at TaskRabbit, I understand that's not where the value lies. It's always been about neighbors helping neighbors. We're just there to make the real-life connection.</p>

<p>I don't know about you, but I think we could all really use a few more real-life connections at the moment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
